the range of free testosterone. I I I
know have you already stated that uh on
the channel many times you don't like
just blanket numbers, but people are
always asking about uh free testosterone
ranges, but is it really important? Is
it the free testosterone that makes you
feel better?
>> Yes, but that doesn't mean that
everything else is moot. uh free
testosterone is certainly essential and
uh you know everyone always wants ranges
right so I'm going to give you a range
but I'm going to give it to you with an
asterisk and that asterisk is that it is
not a range that is a one-sizefits-all
there are people that feel better
slightly below there are very rare few
people that do need a little bit more um
and I hate saying that because every
guys always think more is better with
testosterone so they're always going to
say hey I'm the guy that needs more and
I will tell you there are a lot of side
effects that come with higher free tea
And oftentimes what guys refer to as
estrogen side effects, they're actually
high free tea side effects. So um that
comes from crushing their SHBG with
improper protocols and uh that lowers
your total tea which makes them think
they need more tea which actually
exacerbates the problem of further
lowering SHBG and increasing free tea.
It's a vicious cycle which is very
difficult to explain to patients. When I
train providers, I put this on a
whiteboard to to make sense of it for
them, but it's a little hard for people
to visualize until they truly understand
what's going on. Um, free tea, most of
my guys, I would say 90% of my men
report feeling symptom resolution to an
extent when their free tea falls in a
range of between 20 nanogs per deciliter
and 35 nanogs per deciliter. That is
generally where you're going to find the
biggest uh proportion of of of people
who report resolution to some of the
symptoms on their atom score. You're
going to have the outliers below where
they may be at 17 18 anogs and they feel
great. You may have the guys that you
know in that range that don't feel well
and you got to push them a little bit
and that's rare. Uh but overall I would
say in an anog uh uh scenario that is
where uh most fall in. And I will say
that a lot of labs check pogs per
milliliter. You got to move the decimal
over to the left one to convert to
nanogs. And then you have nanom moles
over in Europe which is a completely
different formula. That is 28.8 multiple
uh to get the nanog number. So uh you
got to do a little bit of math. But I
would just here's the thing to alleviate
all this possible confusion. My answer
is always the same. Find a competent
provider who truly understands this
stuff and then the rest will just fall
into place.